(lively music)
- [Instructor] The next very important,
very important concept is
that of the marginal utility.
Marginal in a sense means incremental
and marginal Utility is the
notion or the name we give
to how sensitive is the satisfaction level
to increases in the
consumption of one good.
Let me repeat that.
Marginal utility is a measure
of what is the impact of
consuming more of one good
on the satisfaction
level or utility level.
So technically, the marginal
utility of commodity X1
is a rate of change of the total utility
as a quantity of it
consume of X1 increases
that hopefully it's
ringing some mathematical
notions that you have learned
in your calculus courses.
And in particular, the
marginal utility is nothing but
something you already know
and that is the notion
of a partial derivative.
A partial derivative is
the mathematical element
or the mathematical concept
that is associated with marginal utility.
The partial derivative is
the mathematical concept
associated with marginal utility.
The same thing is true for
marginal utility of good two.
It is just the partial of
the utility with respects
with respect to X2.
Again, marginal utility of X1,
meaning the impact of
X1 on the utility level
is simply mathematically
the partial derivative
of the utility function with respect to X1
and the marginal utility of X2
is the partial derivative
of the utility function
with respect to good two,
to the consumption of
good two, meaning X2.
Go back and think of what being
a good and neutral or a bad
meant in terms of marginal utility
and I can give you that
summary quickly right now.
So, a commodity is good if
marginal utility is positive.
A commodity is bad if
marginal utility is negative.
A commodity is neutral if
marginal utility is zero.
However, okay, also marginal
utility can be decreasing
or increasing.
So not only utility can be
increasing or decreasing,
in most cases we will
assume that it's increasing
but the marginal, the impact
or the increment of utility
with respect to the increments in X1
denoted as the marginal utility
can also be increasing
or decreasing in X1.
To know whether MUx, MU1 for example, MUx1
is increasing with respect
to or increasing in X1,
we simply take again the derivative of MU1
with respect to X1.
That is, we calculate
this partial derivative.
Let's do, let us do some examples with
one of the non-preferences
and then we will go back to the slides.
Examples of marginal utility. Sorry.
Okay so, let's start with this.
Example, so we're going to have utility.
We're going to start with some form,
one kind of cab daggers so
it's going to be X1 1/2 X2.
So, the marginal utility
of good one would be again,
the partial of the utility
with respect to X1.
And so how do we do this in this case?
Well, notice that first
we have this term here,
we need to take derivatives of
and the second term, this one
does not depend on X1.
So we pretty much need to
use only the second term.
So it's gonna be 1/2
because of the exponent X1.
Now the exponent minus one,
which is gonna be 1/2 minus one,
which take us to minus 1/2
and then we need to multiply
by X2 because X2 is not...
we're not using that to take derivatives.
Therefore, with respect to
what we're doing is a constant
so we need to multiply it.
Okay, so this would be MU, MU1.
We can also calculate MU2
which is the partial derivative
of utility with respect to X2.
in this particular case now,
notice that we need to
do this one first, X2
and then just multiply
by this whole thing.
So, the derivative of
X2 with respect to X2
is simply one.
So we could simply write one
times now X1 power to 1/2
which is simply X1 power to 1/2.
What would happen in a
different example in which
example two in which we
have utility X1, X2 squared.
So let's do MU1 is the partial
of U with respect to X1.
This would be the partial of this
which is just one times this.
So this would be one times X2 squared.
And then for MU2, we would have again
the partial of U with respect to X2,
we would have in a sense X1 again
because that's simply
multiplying times two
because of the exponent of
X2 times X2 because it's,
you know it's the exponent minus one
which is two minus one and one.
So in other words, it's
simply two times X1 times X2.
That will be MU2.
Now let's do a third example
for perfect substitutes.
So we're gonna use one of the...
Let's start with some numbers
like it's gonna be two
times X1 plus let's say
three times X2.
That's gonna be our utility function
as perfect substitutes in
this case is alpha equals two,
beta equals three.
Not that we need to write
it always like that but
that is what our example is this time.
So, this example is very simple
so we're gonna do it very quickly.
MU1 is the partial of U with
respect to X1 in this case,
then X1 is only multiplied by
two and nothing else because
X2, X1 is not here.
So in this case, this is the simplest.
It just be...
it's gonna be just two.
Similarly, MU2 is going to be simply three
because of this term.
And that's it.
That's going to be it.
(lively music)